本劇改編自聖經  它們曾改變世界，直到如今
本劇將始終保持《聖經》真諦
第09集-受難
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
起初  上帝創造天地
In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
神說  要有光
And God said, "Let there be light."
亞當和夏娃違背了上帝的旨意  偷食禁果
Adam and Eve disobeyed God and ate the forbidden fruit.
從那之後  該隱殺了亞伯
Since then, since Cain killed Abel,
上帝目睹了人類內心深處太多的惡念
God has seen too much evil in human hearts.
上帝警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
上帝同我說話了
God has spoken to me.
他將指引我們去新的家園
He will lead us to a new home.
他保證我的後裔會多如繁星
He has promised descendents as numerous as the stars.
-你是誰  -我是摩西
- Who are you? - My name is Moses.
上帝派我回來  釋放你們得自由
God has sent me to set you free.
主帶我們離開了埃及
The Lord brought us out from Egypt.
他承諾將賜予我們這片土地
He promised us this land!
很快  它就會是我們的了
Soon it will be ours!
耶路撒冷  我們的新家園
Jerusalem, our new home.
大衛  你在人間建立了上帝的國度
David, you have forged God's nation on earth.
上帝已經拋棄你了
God has forsaken you.
他想找一個合他心意的人
He wants a man after his own heart.
我相信您的兒子必是其子民未來的王
I believe your son is the promised king of his people.
他叫什麼名字
What is his name?
耶穌
Jesus.
他的名字是耶穌
His name is Jesus.
即將到來的那一位  大過我
There is one to come, greater than me,
我不過是曠野中的吶喊   做好準備迎接
I am just the voice in the wilderness, preparing the way for the...
上帝
Lord.
-過些日子我們就去耶路撒冷  -太危險了
- Soon we go to Jerusalem. - It's too dangerous.
這個來自加利利的擾亂者  是個麻煩
This agitator from Galilee, he's trouble.
-他要去哪裡  -朝聖殿而去  大祭司
- Where is he headed? - Towards the temple, High Priest.
上帝會將他的忿怒降在所有人身上
God will bring his wrath down upon all of us,
誰知道彼拉多會做什麼
and who knows what Pilate will do?
大人  有個猶太人最近在聖殿裡惹麻煩
Sir, a Jew has been causing trouble in the temple.
上帝和金錢  你無法兩者都事奉
You cannot serve God and money.
倘若動亂在明日再次發生
If disturbance took places a day and repeated tomorrow.
我會立即關閉聖殿
I will shut the temple immediately.
毀了這殿  我會在三日之內重新建立起來
Destroy this temple and I will build it again in three days.
他還威脅說要摧毀聖殿
He has threatened to destroy the temple.
我們得除掉他  否則羅馬人會毀滅一切
We remove this man, or the Romans destroy everything.
-處死  -沒錯
- Execute? - Yes.
犧牲這平民的命
The life of one peasant...
換取上帝之國的未來
for the future of God's nation.
我不會離開你
I will not fall away.
彼得  你要三次說不認得我
Peter, you will deny me three times.
-不  -快跑  耶穌
- No! - Run, Jesus!
快跑
Run!
告訴該亞法我們抓到耶穌了
Tell Caiaphas we have Jesus.
-耶穌被捕了  -被捕
- Jesus has been arrested. - Arrested?
-你是不是神的兒子  -我是
- Are you the Son of God? - I am.
詛咒聖名之人
Blasphemer!
聖經
耶路撒冷
逾越節前12個小時
僅供學習 禁止用於任何商業盈利行為
更多影視更新
請登陸 www.YYeTs.com
■
本字幕由YYeTs人人影視翻譯第一版
由Matt K Fu 以基督徒角度作編修
僅供學習 禁止用於任何商業盈利行為
翻譯：sakura櫻 CiCiXT 賀天天 小琪777 和小蟹 袋小待 茶炒栗子 海倫
校對：威廉  蓬蓬裙  sienna      時間軸：魚骨頭
後期：魚骨頭      總監：不要叫我馬維斯
逾越節的聖衣  大祭司
Your Passover robes, High Priest.
這是要判死刑的  但不能用石頭打死
The sentence is death, but it cannot be by stoning.
褻瀆神的懲罰自該如此
It's the penalty for blasphemy.
群眾中
The crowds-
有很多是他的支持者
He has thousands of supporters.
事態很容易失控  我不敢冒這個險
It could be disastrous. I dare not risk it.
彼拉多
Pilate.
讓彼拉多殺他  他有這權利
Pilate can do it. He has the authority.
可是羅馬要以什麼理由處死耶穌
Why would the Romans execute Jesus?
彼拉多奉命保證猶太地區的安全
Pilate is charged with keeping peace in Judaea.
這是共同利益
It's in our common interest.
我得讓他明白這一點
I must make him see that.
在此公告   長老院經過庭審後認為
Let it be known, Jesus of Nazareth has been tried
拿撒勒人耶穌
by the supreme court of elders,
褻瀆神的罪名成立
and he has been found guilty of blasphemy...
威脅損毀聖殿罪名成立
and of threatening to destroy the temple.
你們要他做什麼
What do you want with him?
就是談談
Just to talk.
判刑為...
The sentence...
死刑
is death.
你  還你錢
You! Take back your money!
你
You.
我見過你  你認識他
I've seen you before. You know him.
不
No.
我不認識他
I don't know him.
你管他叫拉比
You called him Rabbi.
他跟我沒關系
He has nothing to do with me.
你認識他  我見過你倆在一起
You know him, I've seen you with him.
我不認識他
I don't know him.
彼得
Peter,
你要三次說不認得我
you will deny me three times.
別怕
Don't be afraid.
帶他去彼拉多那裡
Take him to Pilate.
我的妻子呢  已經很晚了
Where's my wife? It's late.
主人  請快來
Please master, come quickly!
革老底亞  怎麼了
Claudia, what?
我
I-
我在夢裡
I saw a man...
見到一個人
in a dream.
被毆打...
A man being beaten...
然後被殺
and killed.
他是無辜的
An innocent man!
是聖人
A holy man.
是個好人
A good man.
-把她扶上床  -不
- Help your lady back to bed. - No.
殺他的人  是你
It was you who killed him.
你們中有一位
One of you here...
將出賣我
will betray me.
大祭司該亞法和長老們來見你了
Sir, the High Priest Caiaphas and the elders are here to see you.
總督大人  早上好
Prefect, good morning.
總督大人  我們需要你的幫助
Prefect, we need your help.
我們已將一個危險犯人緝拿歸案
We have convicted a dangerous criminal.
他必須被判死刑
His sentence must be death.
那就處死他
So? Execute him.
我們不能
We cannot.
逾越節如此臨近
This close to Passover,
會使我們看起來不聖潔
it would make us impure.
那就逾越節過後再處決
So do it after Passover.
他是個直接威脅
He is an immediate threat...
不僅對我們  也是對你
not only to us, but to you.
現在局勢緊張
This is a tense time...
我的子民在慶祝他們
when my people celebrate...
擺脫了上任欺壓者的魔爪
their deliverance from past oppressors.
他自稱為王
He claims to be our king...
煽動眾人一起反抗
and is whipping up the crowds into a rebellion,
這場反抗能把耶路撒冷搞得四分五裂
a rebellion that could tear Jerusalem apart.
該撒不會高興的
Caesar would not be pleased.
-他的名字  -拿撒勒人耶穌
- His name. - Jesus of Nazareth.
你最好別浪費我時間
You better not be wasting my time.
我會去見那犯人
I'll see the prisoner.
你  請停下
You! Stop, please.
請等等  求你了
Please wait! Please!
你認識耶穌  你和他說過話
You know Jesus. You spoke to him.
求你了  我的兒子在哪兒
Please, where's my son?
-他走了  -走了  去哪了
- He's gone.  - Gone? Where?
-別走  -求您了
- No. - Please.
-他被羅馬人抓走了  -羅馬人
- The Romans have him.  - The Romans?
他從未說過羅馬的壞話
He's never said anything against Rome.
那麼
So,
告訴我你是誰
tell me who you are.
你是猶太人的王嗎
Are you the king of the Jews?
這話是你自己說的
Are you asking,
還是別人論我對你說的呢
or is it a question coming from others?
你是王麽
Are you a king?
你們人民和大祭司告訴我
That's what your own people and chief priest...
你自稱為王
tell me you claim to be.
我的國
My kingdom...
不屬這世界
is not of this world.
我的國若屬這世界
If it were,
我的臣僕必要爭戰  使我不至於被交給猶太人
my servants would fight my arrest.
只是我的國不屬這世界
My kingdom is from another place.
這樣  你是王麽
You are a king then.
你說我是王
You say that I am a king.
我為此而生
I have been born...
也為此來到世間
and come into the world...
要為給真理作見證
to testify to the truth.
凡屬真理的人
Everyone on the side of truth...
就會聽我的話
listens to me.
真理
Truth?
真理是什麼呢
What is truth?
那就是他
That's him.
我在夢中看到的男人  就是他
The man I saw in the dream. That's him!
他們想把他釘十字架
They want him crucified.
你不能這麼做
You can't.
他們說他會引發暴動
They say he could start a revolution.
你不必這樣做
You mustn't!
如果我不這麼做
If I don't,
該亞法會將暴動怪罪於我
Caiaphas will blame any rebellion on me,
該撒會認為那是我的過錯
Caesar will see it as my failure.
他已經警告過我一次
He has warned me once.
不會再給我第二次機會了
He is not going to warn me again.
那我就完了
I'll be finished.
我們就都完了
We'll be finished.
此人的罪行不過是有臆想症
He's guilty of nothing more than being deluded.
他觸犯了律法
He has broken the law.
是你的律法  而非該撒的
Your law, not Caesar's.
放他出來  教他點禮數
Get him out and teach him some respect.
打四十鞭
Forty lashes.
四十鞭
Forty lashes?
僅此而已嗎
Nothing more?
總督大人
Prefect,
眾人的一心企望著上帝
we cannot be held responsible...
倘若你釋放了一個
for what the people may do today...
觸犯我們神聖律法的人
with their eyes on God...
他們今日會做出何等舉動
if you release a man...
我們將無法負責
who has broken our sacred laws.
眾人
The people?
該撒頒布法令說
Caesar decrees...
在逾越節  我可以釋放一名犯人
I can release a prisoner at Passover.
那就讓眾人決定我手中哪一名犯人
Let the people decide which of the prisoners I hold...
將被釘上十字架
will be crucified.
過來
Come on!
動作快  跟上
Move your feet! Come on!
過來
Come on!
這兒  快跟上
Here! Quickly!
他們對他做了什麼
What have they done to him?
他們想要殺了他
They're going to kill him!
似乎一切都在他的預料之中
It's as if he knows this must happen.
這麼說你是王
So you're a king.
每個王都需要一個冠冕
Every king needs a crown.
站起來
Get up!
讓他們進來
Let them in.
-沒錯  -你  你  還有你
- Yes.  - You. You and you.
-你  -你
- You.  - You.
-沒錯  -你
- Yes.  - You.
在那兒等著
Wait there.
不  你不行  回去  回去
No, not you. Back. Back.
不  退後  你不行  回去
No! Step back! Not you. Back.
不要推擠
No pushing!
讓我過去吧
Let me through!
回去  不行  不行
Back! No. No.
讓開
Gets the way!
關上門
Close the gates!
馬利亞  馬利亞  走吧
Hey! Mary! Mary, move.
走吧  我們走
Move. Let's go.
今天  逾越節開始了
Today, Passover begins.
你們的王  該撒提庇留
And your emperor, Tiberius Caesar,
將向民眾廣施恩澤以表祝福
makes you a gesture of good will-
隨眾人所要的
the release of a prisoner-
釋放一個囚犯給你們
chosen by you.
選擇權在你們
I give you a choice.
是巴拉巴
Barabbas-
一個危險的作亂者
a dangerous agitator,
和臭名昭著的殺人犯
a common murderer.
還是這個傳道者
Or this preacher,
他自稱是你們的王
who claims to be your king.
他才不是我們的王
He is not our king!
我們的王  只有該撒
We have no king but Caesar.
你們必須做出選擇
You must decide.
我們選巴拉巴
We choose Barabbas.
-釋放巴拉巴  -巴拉巴
- Free Barabbas. - Barabbas.
他是我們的兄弟
He's one of us.
釋放巴拉巴給我們
Give us Barabbas!
巴拉巴  巴拉巴
Barabbas! Barabbas!
釋放耶穌  釋放耶穌
Jesus! Jesus!
巴拉巴  巴拉巴
Barabbas! Barabbas!
你們選擇殺人犯
You choose a murderer?
釋放巴拉巴給我們
Give us Barabbas!
執行吧
Do it!
跟我走
Let's go.
那這先知呢
And the prophet?
這等僭妄之人怎麼會是我們的王呢
How could this blasphemer be our king?
他才不是我們的王
He's not our king.
把他釘十字架
Crucify him!
處死他
Kill him!
把他釘十字架
Crucify him!
-赦免他  -救救他
- Spare him! - Save him!
-處死他  -把他釘十字架
- Kill him! - Crucify him!
了結他這痛苦的生命吧
Put him out of his misery!
-把他釘十字架  -把他釘十字架
- Crucify him! - Crucify him!
把他釘十字架
Crucify him!
你們怎能處決這人  卻赦免殺人犯呢
How can you condemn this man and spare a murderer?
把他釘十字架
Crucify him!
僭妄者
Blasphemer!
好吧
Very well.
把他釘十字架
Crucify him!
除掉他吧
Let him die!
不要
No!
你  退後
You! Get back!
請釋放他吧
Release him!
快走
Move!
羅馬人渣
Roman scum!
他們怎能如此對他
How can they treat him like this?
約翰  我要去見他
John, I need to see him.
我要去見我的兒子
I need to see my son.
退後
Get back!
快走
Move them back!
和散那  和散那  和散那
Hosanna! Hosanna! Hosanna!
後邊去
Get back there!
羅馬殺手
Roman murderers!
不  耶穌  來人幫幫他
No! Jesus! Somebody help him!
可憐可憐他吧
Show him mercy!
不要
No!
退後  別過來
Get back! Stay back!
我的孩子
My son.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
對上帝而言  萬事皆有可能
Everything is possible with God.
快走
Move forward!
耶穌  耶穌
Jesus! Jesus!
求你們了  她是他母親
Please, she's his mother!
退後  後邊去
Get back! Further back!
退後
Get back!
來人幫幫他
Somebody help him!
求你們了
Please!
你
You!
幫他背十字架
Help him carry the cross.
快走
Move!
我的主
My Lord.
總督大人  他十字架上的牌子要怎麼寫
What will the sign on his cross say, Prefect?
用希伯來  羅馬  希利尼三語書寫
Put in Arqmaic, Latin and Greek
"猶太人的王  拿撒勒人耶穌"
"Jesus of Nazareth, the king of the Jews."
他從不是我們的王
He was never our king.
必須寫作  "這個人自稱...
It must read, "This man said...
我是猶太人的王"
'I am the king of the Jews."'
我說什麼就是什麼  寫猶太人的王
It stays as I 've commanded. The king of the Jews.
懦夫
Cowards!
滾開
Get away!
我的主  保佑你
My Lord. Bless you.
謝謝
Thank you.
快點  動起來
Come on! Move!
快走
Move it!
Move!
快點  說你呢  趕上
Come on! Hey, come on!
快點  快走
Faster! Move!
你  走開  走開
You! Leave! Leave!
快走
Move!
來吧  王
Come on, king.
快點
Come on!
來吧  開始吧
Come on. Come on!
把他放到十字架上
Get him up on the cross!
快點
Come on!
不准靠近了
No further.
綁緊繩子
Secure the ropes.
猶太人的王  拿撒勒人耶穌[三語書寫]
你將為此事悔恨終生
You'll live to regret this.
我們又不是第一次殺猶太人了
Hardly the first Jew we've killed.
他不一樣
He was different.
他是眾神選中的人
He was chosen by the gods.
他以為他是
He thought he was.
一周之內  他就會被遺忘
He'll be forgotten in a week.
把他拉起來
Get him up there!
穩住
Steady!
我的兒啊
My son.
猶太人的王
King of the Jews!
在上面能看到聖殿嗎
Can you see the temple from there?
滾開
Leave him.
父阿
Father!
原諒他們
Forgive them,
他們不知道自己在做什麼
for they know not what they do.
你先來
You first.
真不走運
Bad luck.
你不是彌賽亞嗎
Aren't you the Messiah?
救你自己和我們吧
Why don't you save yourself and us?
我們受刑
Our punishment
是罪有應得
is just,
然而這個人...
but this man...
並沒有作過什麼不對的事
has done nothing wrong.
你的國降臨的時候  求你記念我
Remember me when you come into your kingdom.
我實在告訴你
Truly I say to you,
今天
today,
你必定同我在樂園裡了
you will be with me in paradise.
母親
Mother,
以後他就是你兒子
this is your son.
約翰
John,
她就是你的親娘
this is your mother.
我的神
My God.
為甚麼離棄我
Why have you forsaken me?
我口渴
I thirst.
結束了
It's finished.
父阿
Father,
我把我的靈魂
into your hands...
交在你手裡
I commend my spirit.
-克勞迪婭  -這是一個征兆
- Claudia!  - This is an omen.
把屍體搬走
Take the body away.
等等
Wait!
我這有本丟．彼拉多的命令
I have an order from Pontius Pilate.
屍體是我們的
This body is ours.
給他們
Give it to them.
三天後
你去哪兒了
Where were you?
你本應是他的基石
You were supposed to be his rock.
我辜負了他
I failed him.
如今我不能請求他原諒我
Now I can't ask him to forgive me.
如果有任何需要就回來
Come back if you need anything.
我會的
I will.
祝你回加利利一路平安
Have a safe journey back to Galilee.
願主保佑你
Bless you.
你在找誰
Who are you looking for?
若是你把他移了去  請告訴我他在哪裡
If you've taken him, tell me where he is.
馬利亞
Mary.
夫子
Teacher?
去告訴我們的弟兄們
Go and tell our brothers...
我回來了
I am here.
《聖經》下集預告
Next time on The Bible.
墓穴打開了  我看見他了
The tomb is open. I saw him!
彼得
Peter?
他沒死  他回來了
He hasn't gone. He's back.
你看見我了
Because you see me,
說明你信我
you believe.
不  這不是真的
No, this isn't real.
多馬  不要疑惑
Thomas, stop doubting.
真的是你
It is you.
當聖靈降臨在你們身上
When the holy spirit comes to you,
你們就必領受能力
you will receive power.
我奉耶穌基督的名  叫你起來行走
In the name of Jesus Christ, rise up and walk.
耶穌顯靈了
Jesus did this!
他們又在喊那個低賤之人的名字了
They're shouting that wretched man's name again!
如果你們再妖言惑眾
You will be silent,
我就讓你們再也出不了聲
or you will be silenced.
你褻瀆了神
Blasphemer!
我們不怕死
We are not afraid of death.
大數的保羅
Paul of Tarsus.
我能為你除掉這個渣滓
I could flush this scum out for you.
告訴你的朋友
Tell all your friends
我  大數的保羅
that I, Paul of Tarsus,
必找到你
will find you!
你是誰
Who are you?
告訴我你是誰
Tell me who you are!
寬恕我  我得罪了神
Forgive me. I've wronged God.
所有人皆可進此門
The door is open to everyone.
你必須和我們走一趟
You must come with us.
我們於苦難中歡欣
We rejoice in our suffering.
雅各
James!
不
No!
不再有死亡
There will be no more death...
也不再有悲哀
or mourning...
哭號
or crying...
疼痛
or pain.
總有東西要留傳下去
Something must survive.
如果我不活不了
If not me,
至少要讓我的話留傳下去
then my words at least.
我必快來
I am coming soon.